A Guide to the Requests for Certification to take the Written Bar Exam, 1897-1909
Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
Requests for Certification to take the Written Bar Exam, 1897-1909
Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
000
1.8 cu. ft. (4 boxes)
Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the State Law Library from the Office of the Clerk to the State Law Library in 2006.
Historical Information
In 1895, the General Assembly enacted legislation transferring responsibility for examining prospective lawyers from the circuit court to the higest court in the state, the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia. The Supreme Court of Appeals established rules that provided for a written examination to be held in Richmond, Staunton, and Wytheville at different times of year while the court was in session. The examinations were open to anyone, regardless of education or legal training, provided he was at least 21 years old, a resident of Virginia for six months, and able to produce a 'Certificate of Honest Demeanor from his local circuit court.'" The new rules took effect July 1, 1896. (See J. Gordon Hylton, "The Written Bar Examination and the Development of the Modern Legal Profession in Virginia," Richmond Law, Summer 1991 Vol. 4, No. 2, p. 6.)
An act approved by the General Assembly March 14, 1910, established the Virginia Board of Bar Examiners and authorized it to license lawyers and determine the qualifications of applicants who wished to take the bar examination. The Board served under the auspices of the Supreme Court of Appeals.
Scope and Content
The collection contains letters and recommendations from individuals seeking certification to take the written bar exam from the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1897-1909. For some individuals listed, the only record is a letter requesting the clerk to transfer records to Staunton or Wytheville.
The letters are arranged chronologically and alphabetically within each year.
The collection also contains two folders of correspondence, 1902-1929, from attorneys licensed to practice in other states requesting admission to the Virginia bar.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Part of these records were likely tranferred to the Library of Virginia in 1981 by the Clerk of the Supreme Court of Virginia. Law license applications, 1898-1899, and failed bar examinations, 1903-1906, are part of the collection, Records of the Supreme Court of Appeals, 1871-1914 (accession number) 31211.
Contents List
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1897
  - Brown, Jacob M. (Nelson County)
  - Bronaugh, Minor Bronaugh (Rockbridge County)
  - Chandler, F.W. (Caroline County)
  - Dabney, J.C. (Albemarle County)
  - Davies, J. Jenkins (Prince William County)
  - David, William T. (Petersburg)
  - English, Edward B. (City of Richmond)
  - Flagg, Arthur I. (Fairfax County)
  - Harman, Thomas H. (Floyd County)
  - Jackson, John B. (City of Richmond)
  - Johnston, C.D. (City of Richmond)
  - Newhill, Frank G. (Lancaster County)
  - Rew, John R. (Accomack County)
  - Scott, C.W. (Lynchburg)
  - Sturgis, W.D. (Accomack County)
  - Wayt, Hampton H. (Staunton)
  - Willis, Joseph W. (Alexandria)
  - Woodhouse, J.P. (Princess Anne County)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1898
  - Boisseau, Preston (Nottoway County)
  - Boschen, Albert O. (City of Richmond)
  - Brockenbrough, Lloyd W. (Northampton County)
  - Casabona, Louis (City of Norfolk)
  - Clark, John D. (Lynchburg)
  - Cline, W.P. (City of Richmond)
  - Coke, Jr., John Archer (City of Richmond)
  - Cooke, William L. (Newport News)
  - Corbitt, James Howard (Southampton)
  - Eckles, W.L. (City of Richmond)
  - Haggerty, John J. (City of Richmond)
  - Heath, Harry Williams (City of Norfolk)
  - Lanier, Alexander Sidney
  - Leake, David H. (Goochland County)
  - Mayo, George H. (Goochland County)
  - Pollard, W.T. (City of Lynchburg)
  - Smith, Augustin R.
  - Stephenson, Percy S. (City of Norfolk)
  - Strode, A.E. (Amherst County)
  - Sutton, Jr., Frank Taylor (City of Richmond)
  - Temple, Thomas (Prince George County)
  - Trinkle, E. Lee (Wythe County)
  - Waddill, G. Edward (Newport News)
  - Wallace, Gustavus B. (Stafford County)
- Requests for certifiation to take the written bar exam, 1899
  - Bland, S. Otis (University of Virginia Law Department)
  - Conner, C.B.
  - Drew, Leslie H. (University of Virginia Law Department)
  - Franklin, Roger B. (City of Richmond)
  - Gordon, W.S.
  - Guerrant, John
  - Jones, Charles P.
  - Marshall, E. Carrington
  - Mooklar, W.T. (Lancaster County)
  - Patterson, James S. (City of Richmond)
  - Whitefield, Peyton
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1900
  - Brandt, Sigmund M. (City of Norfolk)
  - Carter, Emery R.
  - DeJarnette, Jr., Elliott H. (Albemarle County)
  - Deshields, H.G. (Northumberland County)
  - Dodge, H.B. (Prince William County)
  - Echols, W.L. (City of Norfolk)
  - Elliott, J.W. (Floyd County)
  - Finnegan, B.E. (Elizabeth City County)
  - Fitzhugh, George (City of Richmond)
  - Gold, Hunter Boyd (University of Virginia Law Department)
  - Jenkins, A.G. (City of Richmond)
  - Shannonhouse, William T.
  - Sherritt, Homer G. (Charlottesville)
  - Tidler, J.O. (Rappahannock County)
  - Waddy, John Larew (Rockbrdige County)
  - Wortham, G.W. (Caroline County)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1901
  - Carter, E.T.
  - Cousins, C.C. (Manchester)
  - Crumpler, W.M.
  - Davis, Richard J. (Portsmouth)
  - Ellison, W.M. (City of Richmond)
  - Johnson, Charles Massie
  - Lewis, James T. (Henrico County)
  - Love, James M. (Fairfax County)
  - McCallister, W.A.
  - Meredith, Edward (Prince William County)
  - Miller, F.C. (City of Norfolk)
  - Moore, T.V. (Chesterfield)
  - Morris, J. Leslie (Bedford County)
  - Morrison, H.J. (Scott County)
  - Peatross, W. Sam
  - Sinclair, G.B. (Albemarle County)
  - Smith, William
  - Stauffer, William T.
  - Stroud, Augustus T. (City of Norfolk)
  - Thomas, Temple
  - Thomas, J. Lewis (Norfolk County)
  - Triplett, Roderick T. (Norfolk County)
  - Walsh, W. Brantley (Fairfax County)
  - Wingfield, Gustavus A.
  - Wilkins, F. Tucker (Northampton County)
  - Winston, James H.
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1902
  - Altizer, Marvin H. (Roanoke County)
  - Ames, Warner (University of Virginia Law Department)
  - Austin, Branch (Albemarle County)
  - Bailey, W. Norris (City of Richmond)
  - Booker, M.B. (Halifax County)
  - Bragg, S.B. (Brunswick County)
  - Bristow, J.C. (Middlesex County)
  - Davis, Beverly H. (City of Richmond)
  - Dillard, D.W. (Henry County)
  - Drewry, P.D. (Henry County)
  - Elliott, J.W. (Floyd County)
  - Elliott, Milton C. (Albemarle County)
  - Fugate, Robert C. (Washington County)
  - Garrow, John Tommer (Warwick County)
  - Hairston, Samuel W. (Henry County)
  - Heth, Stockton (Radford)
  - Hilldrup, J.W. (Campbell County)
  - Jones, William C. (Gloucester County)
  - Lacy, Lane (City of Richmond)
  - Martin, James G. (City of Norfolk)
  - Moore, C. Ridgeway (Northampton County)
  - Mullen, J.M. (Petersburg)
  - Nelson, George E. (Bath County)
  - Nottingham, Gardner R. (Northampton County)
  - Rogers, Hamilton (Petersburg)
  - Roper, Albert S. (City of Norfolk)
  - Ross, William E. (City of Richmond)
  - Swift, Granville R. (City of Fredericksburg)
  - Tucker, J.R. (Rockbridge County)
  - Tyler, Walter G. (City of Richmond)
  - Waller, G. Gardner (Warren County)
  - Weaver, Aubrey G. (Warren County)
  - Wilkins, John T. (City of Richmond)
  - Willis, Russell H. (City of Richmond)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1903
  - Bagby, A. Julian (King William County)
  - Colvin, Howard T. (Alexandria)
  - Farrier, M.P. (Giles County)
  - Fishburne, George Petrie (Charlottesville)
  - French, K.S.
  - Harris, Thomas S. (York County)
  - Koteen, Meyer (Gloucester County)
  - Lightfoot, Jr., John B. (City of Richmond)
  - Marsh, I. Basye (Northumberland County)
  - Morrison, A.K. (Charlottesville)
  - Parrish, Winston (Albemarle County)
  - Pearson, Harry L. (City of Richmond)
  - Powell, Samuel Peter (Spotsylvania County)
  - Price, Jr., William H. (Charlottesville)
  - Smith, Howard W. (Fauquier County)
  - Snyder, W.T. (Charlottesville)
  - Teiser, Sidney (City of Norfolk)
  - Winston, Francis Byrd (Hanover County)
  - Woodson, B.B. (Cumberland County)
  - Wright, James F. (Albemarle County)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1904
  - Bohannon, James Gordon (Surry County)
  - Cave, William Walter (Rockbridge County)
  - Cole, Thomas Stokeley (Albemarle County)
  - Davies, H. Thornton (Prince William County)
  - Deans, Parke P. (Albemarle County)
  - Dey, Jr., William H. (City of Norfolk)
  - Goolrick, William K. (Albemarle County)
  - Hankins, J.G. (Halifax County)
  - Hudgins, Floyd A. (Newport News)
  - Isaacs, George Grant (City of Richmond)
  - Leonard, James N. (Fairfax County)
  - Lewis, R. Colton (Fairfax County)
  - McCoy, Taylor (Staunton)
  - Morris, George W. (Charlottesville)
  - Peery, Kent Eppa (Rockbridge County)
  - Richards, J. Donald (Fauquier County)
  - Segar, Jr., Arthur S. (Elizabeth City County)
  - Turner, J.M. (City of Richmond)
  - Upton, Robert J. (City of Norfolk)
  - Walker, R.C. (City of Richmond)
  - Wampler, T. Morris (Culpeper County)
  - Wooding, Jr., Harry (Danville)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1905
  - Alexander, J.R.H. (Loudoun County)
  - Armistead, Frank (Newport News)
  - Beverly, L.t. (Newport News)
  - Boyd, E.R. (Albemarle County)
  - Bragg, S.B. (City of Richmond)
  - Brown, C. Beverley (Albemarle County)
  - Collins, William G. (Fairfax County)
  - Crittenden, William L. (University of Virginia)
  - Dinwiddie, H.A. (Charlottesville)
  - Edwards, John E. (Albemarle County)
  - Gresham, Phillip M. (Lancaster County)
  - Jackson, W.M. (Patrick County)
  - Johnson, J.B. (Albemarle County)
  - McClung, Louis (Roanoke County)
  - McCoy, Harry E. (Charlottesville)
  - Miller, John (Russell County)
  - Nelson, Leon M. (Albemarle County)
  - Norton, R.K. (Albemarle County)
  - Overbey, R.
  - Paul, John (Albemarle County)
  - Saunders, Hartley Poe (Charlottesville)
  - Shackleford, S.D. (Roanoke)
  - Walker, Otis P. (Henrico County)
  - Webb, J. McBryde (City of Norfolk)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1906
  - Anderson, J. Homes (Charlottesville)
  - Bassette, Jr., A.W.E. (Elizabeth City County)
  - Bickers, H.C. (Page County)
  - Bond, N. (City of Richmond)
  - Brigham, E. Foster (Albemarle County)
  - Brooke, H. Laurence (Albemarle County)
  - Brown, E. Walton (Charlottesville)
  - Bullock, Otis W. (Charlottesville)
  - Burson, M.E. (Charlottesville)
  - Carter, E.M. (Scott County)
  - Carter, Ellerbe W. (Albemarle County)
  - Cary, Lucious F. (Albemarle County)
  - Chichester, C.H. (Charlottesville)
  - Conrad, Laird L. (Albemarle County)
  - Dalton, T.P. (Charlottesvile)
  - Daniel, Edward M. (Albemarle County)
  - Dulaney, Paul (Bristol)
  - Elliott, J.W. (Floyd County)
  - Faires, Clifgard C. (Albemarle County)
  - Ferguson, A.H. (Winchester)
  - Foreman, A.H. (Albemarle County)
  - Galt, H.B.G. (Albemarle County)
  - Geddy, T.H. (Williamsburg and James City County)
  - Harrison, Edmund C. (City of Richmond)
  - Hubard, Robert T. (Charlottesville)
  - Jones, James Paris (Albemarle County)
  - Joyren, Herbert S. (Charlottesville)
  - Kelly, Emerson W. (Wise County)
  - Kelsey, D.A. (City of Norfolk)
  - Keyes, W.W. (Albemarle County)
  - Kizer, D.H. (Charlottesville)
  - Lewis, H. Stuart (Albemarle County)
  - McCandlish, F.S. (Middlesex County)
  - Monserrat, D. (Albemarle County)
  - Payne, George M. (City of Norfolk)
  - Rust, George M. (City of Norfolk)
  - Shackelford, Virginius R. (Albemarle County)
  - Spratley, C. Vernon (Albemarle County)
  - Stayer, Harry V. (Albemarle County)
  - Stump, Robert W. (Fairfax County)
  - Visanka, Ernest L. (Charlottesville)
  - Wallace, H. Lewis (Fredericksburg)
  - Walsh, Horman W. (Albemarle County)
  - Way, L.B. (Albemarle County)
  - West, Eugene R. (Albemarle County)
  - Wiggs, James O. (City of Roanoke)
  - Wilhelm, William (City of Roanoke)
  - Williams, Ashby (Charlottesville)
  - Williams, Thomas J. (Albemarle County)
  - Woodhouse, Edward J. (Albemarle County)
  - Worth, E. Clay (Charlottesville)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1907
  - Beale, Richard L. (City of Richmond)
  - Cotten, P.S. (City of Norfolk)
  - Eanes, E. Ennis (Charlottesville)
  - Ferrall, E.T. (City of Richmond)
  - Foushee, W.L. (City of Richmond)
  - Garner, Henceford Noel (Alexandria)
  - Geddy, T.H. (City of Williamsburg and James City County)
  - Hanckel, Allan R. (City of Roanoke)
  - Hopwood, A.C. (City of Roanoke)
  - Kerse, T.L. (City of Richmond)
  - Masincup, W.H. (City of Roanoke)
  - McNeil, W.S. (City of Richmond)
  - Monserrat, Damian (Albemarle County)
  - Nelson, Berkeley (Roanoke County)
  - Parker, W.J.
  - Popwell, Jr., J.L. (Spotsylvania County)
  - Purvis, Benjamin (Stafford County)
  - Selby, Innis C. (Middlesex County)
  - Walker, William R. (Albemarle County)
  - Washington, Richard B. (Alexandria)
  - White, William J. (City of Norfolk)
  - Williams, A. Roy (Portsmouth)
  - Williams, Daivd T. (Pittsylvania County)
  - Wilson, Frederick R. (Buchanan County)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1908
  - Arnold, John Murrelle (Rockbridge County)
  - Ball, Frank L. (Alexandria)
  - Beard, Stanley Alphonse (Rockbridge County)
  - Burnette, Gilbert (Albemarle County)
  - Cauthorn, Alexander J. (Bedford County)
  - Fife, William O. (Albemarle County)
  - Gore, B.S. (Bristol)
  - Harrison, James M. (City of Norfolk)
  - Hunter, Thomas Lomax (King George County)
- Requests for certification to take the written bar exam, 1909
  - Burt, W. Stanley (Surry County)
  - Fry, George Washington (Albemarle County)
  - Painter, Gresham M. (Charlottesville)
- Requests for admission to the Virginia bar from lawyers outside the state, 1902-1929
  - Alexander, Henry A. (Georgia) 1908
  - Burke, John T. (Montana) 1915
  - Conrad, Jr., Holmes (North Carolina) 1905
  - Echols, John Warnock (District of Columbia) 1904
  - Gwynn, Walter Ballard (North Carolina) 1908
  - Hill, Jr., Edmund (District of Columbia) 1916
  - Kelly, A.D. (Texas) 1905
  - Kines, Edward S. (Maryland) 1908
  - Ianson, D.T. (South Carolina) 1907
  - Leigh, Jr., William (Maryland) 1915
  - Madison, Andrew D. 1916
  - Mahoney, William Joseph (Kentucky) 1902
  - Partlow, Ira J. (West Virginia) 1916
  - Rowley, Eugene Cooper (Wisconsin) 1910
  - Ryan, E.R. (District of Columbia) 1902
  - Swartz, S.T. 1906
  - Waring, Wingage (South Carolina) 1929
  - Zollicoffer, Dallas B. (North Carolina) 1923